<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Considerations of importance to Ireland in a letter to a member of Parliament there; upon occasion of Mr Molyneaux's late book: intituled, The case of Ireland's being bound by Acts of Parliament in England, stated. Printed anno 1698.</title>
            <author>Leslie, Charles, 1650-1722.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 34 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47738</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1125</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216404</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828135</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828135</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32562</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47738)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32562)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1912:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Considerations of importance to Ireland in a letter to a member of Parliament there; upon occasion of Mr Molyneaux's late book: intituled, The case of Ireland's being bound by Acts of Parliament in England, stated. Printed anno 1698.</title>
                  <author>Leslie, Charles, 1650-1722.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>By Charles Leslie.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: Dec. 26. 1698.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Molyneux, William, 1656-1698 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Case of Ireland's being bound by Acts of Parliament in England.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  Politics and government --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:32562:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:32562:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Conſiderations of Importance TO IRELAND, <hi>In a</hi> LETTER <hi>to a</hi> Member <hi>of</hi> Parliament <hi>there; upon Occaſion of Mr.</hi> Molyneux's <hi>late Book: In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled,</hi> The Caſe of <hi>Ireland</hi>'s being Bound by Acts of Parliament in <hi>England,</hi> Stated. <hi>Printed</hi> Anno 1698.</head>
            <p>MR. <hi>Molyneux</hi> has, I think, demonſtratively prov'd the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> from the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> though not from the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> becauſe he is alſo <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Ireland;</hi> as of <hi>Scotland,</hi> though without any Subjection of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Scotland</hi> to the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>England:</hi> I ſay, he has prov'd this, by undeniable <hi>Matter</hi> of <hi>Fact,</hi> through all the ancient Precedents, down to the Reign of K. <hi>Charles</hi> II.</p>
            <p>But from the Time he produces <hi>Precedents</hi> of ſome <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> which have bound <hi>Ireland.</hi> Againſt which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains as <hi>Innovations:</hi> And which therefore ought not to deſtroy their Ancient <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Freedoms.</hi> And he has beſides <hi>Three</hi> Arguments, by which he wou'd avail the force of theſe <hi>late Precedents,</hi> from being any binding <hi>Law</hi> to <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſo as to diſſolve their Original <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency</hi> upon <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt is, That <hi>there has been no occaſion of Executing thoſe Laws in Ireland;</hi> as he Inſtances, p. 103. upon occaſion of the <hi>Tobacco Act,</hi> i. e. forbidding <hi>Tobacco</hi> to be Planted in <hi>Ireland;</hi> For there is none Planted there: And therefore there has no Caſe happen'd, to diſpute the Vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity of that <hi>Act</hi> made in <hi>England;</hi> and conſequently to know whether <hi>Ireland</hi> has Subjected it ſelf to that <hi>Act?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:32562:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That <hi>Private Perſons</hi> may obey an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Act which relates to <hi>Ireland,</hi> for their own Security, and to avail Trouble or Charge to themſelves: But that this does not infer the <hi>Conſent</hi> or <hi>Submiſſion</hi> of the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> whereby it may be bound by ſuch <hi>Precedents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This may be Pleaded in Relation to the <hi>Engliſh Act of Navigation,</hi> which obliges <hi>Iriſh</hi> Ships, Importing any Goods from our Foreign Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, to Touch firſt at <hi>England.</hi> And the <hi>Engliſh Acts</hi> Prohibiting the Exportation of Wool from <hi>Ireland,</hi> to any Country, except to <hi>England.</hi> Theſe Mr. <hi>Molyneux</hi> mentions, p. 103, 104.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Third</hi> Argument he has, is, That ſome <hi>Acts</hi> have been made in <hi>England,</hi> Relating to <hi>Ireland,</hi> in the Times of ſuch <hi>Wars</hi> and <hi>Confuſions</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> that a <hi>Parliament</hi> could not be held there: And yet that it was thought <hi>Neceſſary,</hi> at leaſt <hi>Beneficial,</hi> to provide for the Safety of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt there, by <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> till ſuch Time as Regular <hi>Parliaments</hi> could be had in <hi>Ireland.</hi> Upon this Head, he endeavours to ſalve ſome <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Parliament,</hi> made ſince this Revolution, which relate to <hi>Ireland.</hi> As the <hi>Act</hi> for the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Iriſh Clergy,</hi> p. 107. And the <hi>Act</hi> for <hi>Security of the Proteſtants</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> p. 109. Both made in the firſt Year of <hi>W.</hi> and <hi>M.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But p. 111. He comes to a very hard Caſe; which is, The <hi>Act</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Parliament,</hi> Abrogating <hi>the Oath of Supremacy in</hi> Ireland, <hi>and Appointing other Oaths.</hi> 3 and 4 <hi>W.</hi> and <hi>M.</hi> c. 2. And, <hi>To this</hi> (ſays he) <hi>the Parliament Conven'd at</hi> Dublin, Anno 1692. <hi>under Lord</hi> Sydney; <hi>and that likewiſe</hi> Anno 1695. <hi>under Lord</hi> Capel, <hi>paid an intire Obedience. And by this</hi> (continues he) <hi>'tis alledged, we have</hi> given up <hi>our</hi> Right, <hi>if any we had; and have for ever acknowledged our Subordination to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of England.</hi> And believe it, it ſeems to be a very ſhrewd <hi>Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</hi> For none of the former <hi>Salvos</hi> will ſerve in this Caſe. Firſt, was not in time of <hi>Wars,</hi> and ſuch <hi>Confuſions,</hi> as to hinder a <hi>Parliament</hi> to be held in <hi>Ireland:</hi> For there was a <hi>Parliament</hi> held there the ſame Year, <hi>Anno</hi> 1692. Secondly, This was not the <hi>Compliance</hi> of <hi>Private Perſons,</hi> but of <hi>Two</hi> ſucceeding <hi>Parliaments,</hi> Anno 1692. and 1695, in <hi>Ireland.</hi> Thirdly, It cannot be ſaid, That <hi>there had been no Occaſion of Executing theſe Laws</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi> For this Act has been <hi>Executed</hi> to the uttermoſt; By this all <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> are Diſabled to ſit in either <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> there. By this, all the <hi>Popiſh,</hi> and one <hi>Proteſtant Peer</hi> have been thruſt out of their <hi>Seats</hi> in the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Peers.</hi> And, by the ſame Rule, all the reſt, and of the <hi>Commons</hi> too, who had not taken Care to qualifie themſelves, purſuant to the <hi>Engliſh Act,</hi> had <hi>forfeited</hi> their <hi>Right</hi> to ſit in <hi>Parliament;</hi> and conſequently, left <hi>Ireland</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <hi>Poſſibility</hi> of any <hi>Parliamant</hi> at all. By this one <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and others of the Inferior <hi>Clergy</hi> have been <hi>Deprived.</hi> By this <hi>Act</hi> ſeveral <hi>Penalties</hi> and <hi>Diſabilities</hi> are impos'd upon Perſons of all <hi>Ranks</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions;</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:32562:2"/>which has been exacted upon all the <hi>Non-Compliers</hi> to the ſaid <hi>Engliſh</hi> Act.</p>
            <p>Now, if a People can give up their own Rights (which according to Mr. <hi>Lock,</hi> &amp;c. (from whom Mr. <hi>Molyneux</hi> takes it) upon Truſt) is the <hi>Original</hi> and <hi>Foundation</hi> of all Government; what more <hi>Authentick</hi> Method can be taken, than to have them <hi>Surrendred</hi> by the <hi>Ceſſion</hi> and <hi>Submiſſion</hi> of the <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> of the <hi>People</hi> in <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a <hi>Material</hi> Point which, if not cleared, makes an end at once, of all the <hi>Pretenſions</hi> that can be ſet up in behalf of the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> for its being <hi>Independant</hi> upon the Kingdom of <hi>England;</hi> and not bound by the <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> even without having any <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> in the <hi>Engliſh Parliament.</hi> That is, That the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as well as <hi>Iriſh,</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> are in the Condition of <hi>Slaves;</hi> and to be diſpoſed of, both as to their <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Fortunes,</hi> without any <hi>Conſent</hi> of their own, by <hi>Themſelves,</hi> or their <hi>Repreſentatives.</hi> For ſuch they have render'd themſelves, by the <hi>intire Obedience</hi> which <hi>Two</hi> of their <hi>Parliaments</hi> Succeſſively have paid to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Act enjoining the <hi>Oaths</hi> there; and by <hi>Executing</hi> the ſame, even in the <hi>Qualifications</hi> for <hi>Members</hi> to ſerve in <hi>Parliament,</hi> which are preſcribed in the ſaid <hi>Engliſh</hi> Act.</p>
            <p>Therefore, it will be worth the while, to ſee what the Ingenious Mr. <hi>Molyneux</hi> has to ſay, in order to Ward off ſo <hi>Fatal</hi> a Concluſion.</p>
            <p>He ſays, p. 111. 112. That this <hi>Submiſſion of the Iriſh Parliament is to be deem'd</hi> as purely Voluntary, <hi>and not at all proceeding from the Right which they conclude thereby in the Legiſlators. If a man</hi> (ſays he) <hi>who has</hi> no Juriſdiction <hi>over me,</hi> Command <hi>we to do a thing that is</hi> Pleaſing <hi>to me, and I do it; it will not thence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that therefore he obtains an</hi> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority <hi>over me, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ever hereafter I muſt</hi> Obey <hi>him of</hi> Duty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>If I</hi> Voluntarily <hi>give my Money to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Man when I</hi> Pleaſe, <hi>and think it</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient <hi>for me; this does <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t Authorize him at any time to</hi> Command <hi>my Money from me when he Pleaſes.</hi> Thus he: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut, under favour, this is a very <hi>Lame</hi> put off; and the Caſe is not ſtated aright. The Caſe is not of one who <hi>has no Juriſdiction over me;</hi> that is, who <hi>Claims</hi> none. For then, there is no <hi>Diſpute:</hi> But the Caſe ſhou'd be put, of one who <hi>Claims</hi> a <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> over me; and then it ought to be conſider'd, how far my <hi>Submiſſion</hi> is to be Conſtrued a Yielding up to him that <hi>Right</hi> over me, which he <hi>Claims.</hi> And ſuch ſort of <hi>Submiſſion</hi> no doubt there is; and has been ſo Rul'd in all <hi>Ages</hi> and <hi>Caſes.</hi> Therefore the preſent Enquiry is, Whether this <hi>Submiſſion</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> be of this ſort or not? And what ſhou'd hinder it? For here is a <hi>Submiſſion</hi> and <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Obedience</hi> of <hi>Two Parliaments</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> to a <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> which the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England</hi> does <hi>Claim</hi> over the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Ireland.</hi> And what can be an <hi>Owning</hi> of this <hi>Claim</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> if this be not? Here is no <hi>Caveat,</hi> or <hi>Reſerve,</hi> put in by the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to ſave this <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> now <hi>Claim'd,</hi> and put in <hi>Practice</hi> by
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:32562:3"/>the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> from being a <hi>Precedent</hi> for the Time to come: But (as Mr. <hi>Molyneux</hi> Words it) an <hi>intire Obedience</hi> paid to the <hi>Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Suppoſe a Man <hi>Claims</hi> a <hi>Paramount Right</hi> to my <hi>Houſe</hi> and <hi>Eſtate;</hi> and <hi>Pretends,</hi> That I am but his <hi>Steward</hi> or <hi>Baily,</hi> and hold only at his <hi>Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure:</hi> And, in purſuance of their pretended <hi>Right,</hi> ſhall iſſue his <hi>Orders</hi> to me, <hi>Limiting</hi> me what <hi>Servants</hi> I ſhall keep, and Admit ſuch and ſuch for <hi>Tenants,</hi> and no other. And if I pay <hi>intire Obedience</hi> to theſe <hi>Orders,</hi> without the leaſt <hi>Interpoſition</hi> in behalf of my own <hi>Right;</hi> and ſhou'd <hi>Execute</hi> theſe <hi>Orders,</hi> as <hi>his Orders,</hi> and not at all as <hi>my own,</hi> or as deriving any <hi>Authority</hi> from <hi>me;</hi> will it ſerve to ſay afterwards, That this was <hi>purely Voluntary</hi> in me; and that I only did what I had a mind to do my ſelf? Wou'd ſuch an <hi>Excuſe</hi> paſs? Wou'd it not appear ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly <hi>Ridiculous:</hi> But eſpecially, if I durſt not make any ſuch <hi>Excuſe</hi> for my ſelf; only another pretended this for me. The <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> has not Adventur'd to ſay any Thing of this, in their own Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half; to enter the leaſt <hi>Proteſt,</hi> or <hi>Salvo</hi> for their own <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency</hi> upon the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> Therefore what is ſaid on their Behalf by others, not any way Authoriz'd by them, cannot be taken as a keeping up of their <hi>Claim.</hi> It is none of their Act; and as they are not <hi>Anſwerable</hi> for it, neither can they keep any <hi>Advantage</hi> by it.</p>
            <p>The next Thing Mr. <hi>Molyneux</hi> Advances, in Behalf of the <hi>People</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> to ſave their <hi>Rights</hi> from the Conſequences of this <hi>Act,</hi> is Page 113. Where he ſays, <hi>That the Right of being Subject</hi> only <hi>to ſuch Laws to which Men give their</hi> own Conſent, <hi>is ſo inherent to all Mankind, and Founded on ſuch Immutable Laws of Nature and Reaſon, that 'tis not to be</hi> Alien'd <hi>or</hi> Given <hi>up, by any Body of Men whatſoever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ſtrikes at the Power of the <hi>Iriſh Parliament,</hi> to <hi>Give up</hi> the <hi>Rights</hi> of the <hi>People</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> as they have done, by their <hi>intire Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> to this Act of the <hi>Engliſh Parliament.</hi> And this, upon two Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations. Firſt, As ſuppoſing that the <hi>People</hi> never meant to <hi>Give up</hi> their <hi>Rights</hi> ſo <hi>intirely</hi> to their <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> in <hi>Parliament,</hi> as to Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power them to <hi>Betray</hi> them, and <hi>Deliver</hi> them <hi>up</hi> to whom they thought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it: And therefore, That any ſuch <hi>Act</hi> or <hi>Conceſſion</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> is <hi>Void,</hi> and not to be <hi>Own'd</hi> by the <hi>People.</hi> Secondly, That ſuppoſing the <hi>People</hi> had Granted their <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> ſuch a Power, yet that the <hi>Grant</hi> was <hi>Void;</hi> becauſe that it was not in the <hi>Peoples</hi> Power to make ſuch a <hi>Grant,</hi> as being againſt <hi>the Immutable Laws of Nature and Reaſon.</hi> I will not enter upon the Diſquiſition of theſe <hi>Topicks,</hi> as being equally againſt the Power of all <hi>Parliaments,</hi> as well in <hi>England</hi> as in <hi>Ireland.</hi> And the Recurring to the <hi>Original Rights</hi> of <hi>Mankind,</hi> antecedent to all <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> and <hi>Frames</hi> of <hi>Government,</hi> carrys with it ſuch long <hi>Conſequences,</hi> as I am not willing to meddle with at preſent: But ſhall
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:32562:3"/>content my ſelf with this, which ſeems to be granted by this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, That as far as it is in the Power of a <hi>Parliament</hi> to <hi>Give up</hi> the <hi>Rights</hi> of a <hi>People,</hi> ſo far has the preſent <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Ireland Given up</hi> the <hi>Rights</hi> of that <hi>People,</hi> to the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> by their <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Obedience</hi> to this <hi>Act.</hi> And what <hi>Other</hi> or <hi>Better</hi> way there is for a <hi>People</hi> to <hi>Give up</hi> their <hi>Rights,</hi> than by their <hi>Repreſentatives</hi> in <hi>Parliament,</hi> I leave it to the Learned to Diſpute.</p>
            <p>I am ſure it is a more <hi>Authentick</hi> way, than what Mr. <hi>Molyneux</hi> does next lay the Streſs upon, p. 114. <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>general Application of the Chief part of the</hi> Iriſh Proteſtants, <hi>that were at that time in</hi> London, <hi>to the</hi> Parliament <hi>at</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>for obtaining theſe Laws:</hi> Which he wou'd improve to infer a <hi>Conſent</hi> of the People of <hi>Ireland:</hi> But this can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver do.</p>
            <p>For, Firſt, This can, in no Senſe, be Conſtru'd ſo <hi>Regular</hi> and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized</hi> a <hi>Repreſentation</hi> of the <hi>People</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> as a <hi>Parliament</hi> freely <hi>Choſen,</hi> and ſitting in <hi>Ireland.</hi> Secondly, The <hi>Application</hi> of theſe <hi>Iriſh Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>London</hi> to the <hi>Parliament</hi> at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> for obtaining of theſe Laws, was a <hi>Giving up</hi> of the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> and <hi>Acknowledging</hi> this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted <hi>Right</hi> of the <hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>England</hi> over <hi>Ireland;</hi> as much as was in theſe <hi>Iriſh Proteſtants</hi> Power to do it. And I am ſure ſome of them were minded of it, at the ſame time. And withal told, That it was to no manner of Purpoſe: For that, if K. <hi>James</hi> (of whom they were afraid) ſhould <hi>Return;</hi> and ſhould think fit to Aſſert the <hi>Laws</hi> made in in that <hi>Parliament</hi> he held in <hi>Ireland,</hi> the <hi>Repeal</hi> of them by a <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> which he did not <hi>Acknowledge,</hi> would ſignify nothing. And till he did not <hi>Return,</hi> they were in no Danger of thoſe <hi>Laws</hi> made to their <hi>Prejudice,</hi> in his <hi>Parliament.</hi> But they have Verify'd the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb, <hi>Too Faſt, too Looſe.</hi> And would not Reſt, till they had Given this <hi>Precedent</hi> againſt Themſelves.</p>
            <p>The reſt that Mr. <hi>Molineux</hi> ſays, to ſave this <hi>Act</hi> Appointing the <hi>New Oaths,</hi> from being a <hi>Surrender</hi> of the <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> is only by way of <hi>Complaint.</hi> P. 114, 115. That <hi>if ſome ſuch Conſiderations as theſe,</hi> (before-mentioned) <hi>may not Plead for <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>we are of all his Majeſty's Subjects the moſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfortunate.</hi> Then he Appeals to the <hi>King's Juſtice,</hi> to Protect the <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and of their <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> as of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> &amp;c. But he may be told, That <hi>Juſtice</hi> does not Relieve any but <hi>Infants,</hi> and <hi>Idiots,</hi> againſt their own <hi>Act</hi> and <hi>Deed.</hi> And that the Queſtion is not now, What <hi>Rights</hi> the <hi>Parliaments</hi> of <hi>Ireland</hi> had <hi>Formerly,</hi> (which Mr. <hi>Molineux</hi> has made appear Plain enough) but whether they have not <hi>Surrendred</hi> them? Particularly, by their <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire Obedience</hi> to this <hi>Act</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Parliament</hi> Appointing the <hi>New Oaths,</hi> and Abrogating the <hi>Old,</hi> Enacted by <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let me here take Notice of the Difference betwixt the Two <hi>Engliſh</hi> Acts; the one for Impoſing the <hi>Oaths</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and the other for Impoſing them in <hi>Ireland.</hi> This Latter has ſet ſuch Prodigious <hi>Penalties</hi> more than the Former, as plainly ſhew the Difference they make twixt
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:32562:4"/>the Condition of <hi>Subjects,</hi> and of <hi>Slaves.</hi> In the Act for <hi>Ireland,</hi> it is Enacted, That if any <hi>Member</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> there, whether of the <hi>Lords</hi> or <hi>Commons,</hi> ſhall preſume to Sit or Vote in <hi>Parliament,</hi> without firſt Qualifying himſelf, as Preſcrib'd in that Act, or any other, ſhall Offend againſt the ſaid Act, they ſhall be thereby Incapable of any <hi>Office, Place,</hi> or <hi>Truſt, Eccleſiaſtical, Civil,</hi> or <hi>Military,</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> as well as <hi>England. And ſhall be Diſabled from thenceforth to Sit or Vote in either Houſe of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of the ſaid Realm of</hi> Ireland, <hi>or make a Proxy in the Houſe of Peers there; or to Sue or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe any Action, Bill, Plaint, or Information in Courts of Law, or to Proſecute any Suit in any Court of Equity; or to be Guardian of any Child; or Executor or Adminiſtrator of any Perſon; or Capable of any Legacy, or Deed of Gift; and ſhall ſorfeit for every wilful Offence againſt this Act, the Sum of Five hundred Pounds, to be Recovered and Received by him, her, or them, that will Sue for the ſame — in any of their Majeſties Courts of Record at</hi> Dublin, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here the <hi>Courts</hi> of <hi>Law</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> are Commanded to Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute this <hi>Engliſh Act,</hi> as the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Ireland.</hi> This <hi>Act,</hi> which <hi>Abrogates</hi> former <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Parliament</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and makes <hi>New</hi> for them, without Asking their Conſent! But it may be ſaid, That it is now too Late. That the Fault is committed. The <hi>Surrender</hi> is made of all the <hi>Liberties</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> by the <hi>Submiſſion</hi> of <hi>Two</hi> ſucceeding <hi>Parliaments:</hi> And therefore not Now to be Recall'd.</p>
            <p>I Anſwer: That there is a Great <hi>Difference</hi> betwixt a <hi>Free</hi> and <hi>Formal Surrender,</hi> upon valuable Conſiderations; and that <hi>Surrender</hi> which is only ſo <hi>Conſtructively,</hi> or by <hi>Conſequence.</hi> The <hi>Firſt,</hi> if made <hi>Validly,</hi> operates <hi>Immediately;</hi> is a <hi>Transferring</hi> of <hi>Right;</hi> and Bars all after <hi>Claim.</hi> But the other Caſe is <hi>Diſputable:</hi> And Allowances muſt be made, for <hi>Inad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertencies,</hi> for <hi>Force,</hi> or <hi>Craft,</hi> or any <hi>ſiniſter Dealing.</hi> And if <hi>Nullum Tempus occurrit Regi,</hi> the ſame Reaſon will hold as to a <hi>Parliament;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they Act for <hi>Others,</hi> in a <hi>Publick</hi> and <hi>General</hi> Capacity. Mr. <hi>Moly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neux,</hi> p. 152. quotes out of Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi> this <hi>Maxim,</hi> viz. <hi>To be Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded we do Conſent, when that Society whereof we are Part, hath at any time before Conſented; without Revoking the ſame after, by the like <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement.</hi> To this Power of <hi>Revocation,</hi> he Limits no <hi>Time.</hi> I will not take upon me to Determine the <hi>Punctum,</hi> when a <hi>Preſcription</hi> does <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence:</hi> Or what <hi>Force</hi> it has; eſpecially in Matters of <hi>Government;</hi> we know Great Uſe is made of it: And in no one thing more than in the <hi>Privileges</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> for which <hi>Preſcription</hi> is the Chief Rule to which they Appeal, in their daily ſearching for <hi>Precedents,</hi> when any Diſpute happens concerning their <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Powers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this Late <hi>Act</hi> concerning <hi>Ireland,</hi> has not yet <hi>Age</hi> enough for a <hi>Preſcription:</hi> And therefore there is yet <hi>Time</hi> for the <hi>Iriſh Parliaments</hi> to Aſſert their <hi>Right,</hi> if any they pretend to have. They may, if they ſo think fit, <hi>Diſown</hi> that <hi>Engliſh Act,</hi> which Abrogates <hi>Oaths</hi> Enjoyn'd by former <hi>Parliaments</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Requires <hi>New Oaths.</hi> And they may <hi>Reſtore</hi> thoſe who have been <hi>Forfeited</hi> by it. This, by Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi>'s and Mr. <hi>Molyneux</hi>'s Rule before-quoted, the <hi>Iriſh Parliament</hi> may yet do. But,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:32562:4"/>by the ſame Rule, till they do it, they are Concluded. And they cannot make any <hi>Pretence</hi> of <hi>Claim</hi> for their <hi>Independency</hi> from the <hi>Parliaments</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> while they <hi>Continue</hi> to Pay <hi>Obedience</hi> to this <hi>Act.</hi> And ſuch <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> they do Pay, while they Continue any under <hi>Forfeitures</hi> Incurr'd by that <hi>Act.</hi> For that is <hi>Executing</hi> of the <hi>Act:</hi> And that is the moſt <hi>Authentick</hi> Manner of <hi>Owning</hi> it. And if they continue ſuch, under theſe <hi>Forfeitures</hi> till they Die, I cannot tell but the Occaſion will be Loſt. However, I am ſure the Longer that <hi>Iriſh Parliaments</hi> continue to Pay Obedience to this <hi>Engliſh Act,</hi> the <hi>Precedent</hi> grows the ſtronger, and works ſtill more towards a <hi>Preſcription.</hi> The Proſpect of this made Mr. <hi>Molineux</hi> thus Paſſionately Expoſtulate, P. 169. <hi>If the Religion,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>Lives, Liberties, Fortunes, and Eſtates of the Clergy, Nobility, and Gentry of</hi> Ireland, <hi>may be Diſpoſed of, without their Privity and Conſent, What Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit have they of any Laws, Liberties, or Privileges granted unto them by the Crown of</hi> England? <hi>I am loath to give their Condition a Hard Name; but I have no other Notion of</hi> Slavery, <hi>but being Bound by a Law to which I do not Conſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>May it not now be worth Enquiring, How this Single <hi>Act,</hi> this <hi>only,</hi> of Impoſing the <hi>New Oaths,</hi> ſhou'd Prove ſuch a <hi>Mill-Stone</hi> to the Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> as to Carry with it All the <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Freedom</hi> of that <hi>Country</hi> into the Bottom of the <hi>Sea!</hi> Shall we ſay, That this is only by <hi>Chance?</hi> Some Men Refer <hi>All</hi> to that. But I think there is a much more <hi>ſerious</hi> and <hi>ſubſtantial</hi> Reflection which this will Afford Us; And, if it be not yet Quite out of Faſhion to uſe that Word, a <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Conſideration.</p>
            <p>By this <hi>Act,</hi> and by this <hi>Only,</hi> one <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and ſeveral <hi>Clergy-men</hi> of <hi>Ireland,</hi> are <hi>Depriv'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if it be <hi>Sacrilege</hi> to <hi>Rob</hi> God's <hi>Church,</hi> how much more His <hi>Prieſts?</hi> There is nothing <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Holy</hi> but <hi>God.</hi> But there is a Relative <hi>Holineſs,</hi> as things belong more <hi>Peculiarly</hi> to Him. Thus <hi>Iſrael</hi> was call'd an <hi>Holy</hi> (tho' otherwiſe a very <hi>wicked</hi>) Nation; that is, in Compariſon of other <hi>Nations,</hi> who were not in <hi>Federal League</hi> or <hi>Covenant</hi> with <hi>God.</hi> And <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was call'd the <hi>Holy City,</hi> more than All the other <hi>Cities</hi> of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> The <hi>Temple</hi> was more <hi>Holy</hi> than <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> And that Part of it within the <hi>Veil,</hi> more <hi>Holy</hi> than the Reſt of the <hi>Temple;</hi> therefore call'd, The <hi>Holy</hi> of <hi>Holies.</hi> Not that <hi>Stones</hi> or <hi>Lime</hi> are in themſelves <hi>Holy,</hi> or one <hi>Holier</hi> than Another; But only as they Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated more nearly to the Service of <hi>God.</hi> Thus <hi>Iſrael</hi> was more <hi>Holy</hi> than other <hi>Nations:</hi> The <hi>Levites</hi> more <hi>Holy</hi> than the <hi>People</hi> of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> The <hi>Prieſts</hi> more <hi>Holy</hi> than the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vites:</hi> And the <hi>H. Prieſt</hi> more <hi>Holy</hi> than the other <hi>Prieſts.</hi> Not that the <hi>H. Prieſt</hi> muſt neceſſarily be a more <hi>Holy</hi> Man in himſelf than All or Any of the other <hi>Prieſts;</hi> That the <hi>Prieſts</hi> muſt be more <hi>Holy</hi> than the <hi>Levites;</hi> or Every <hi>Levite,</hi> than <hi>All</hi> the Reſt of the People of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> But this was in regard to their <hi>Office,</hi> and more near Deſignation ſo the <hi>Service</hi> and <hi>Worſhip</hi> of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now <hi>Sacrilege</hi> is not the <hi>Robbing</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in His <hi>Perſon,</hi> for that is Impoſſible: But in thoſe Things that <hi>Relate</hi> unto <hi>Him.</hi> And the <hi>Sacrilege</hi> Riſes <hi>Higher,</hi> as it comes <hi>Nearer</hi> to what is <hi>Near</hi> unto <hi>Him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Therefore, as the <hi>Holineſs</hi> of <hi>Inanimate</hi> Things; as of <hi>Temples, &amp;c.</hi> is not ſo Great as the <hi>Holineſs</hi> (tho' <hi>Relative</hi>) of <hi>Perſons:</hi> So the <hi>Sacrilege</hi> is Greater of Robbing Holy <hi>Perſons,</hi> than Holy <hi>Things.</hi> It had been Greater <hi>Sacrilege</hi> to have Robb'd <hi>Aaron</hi> of his <hi>Holy Veſements,</hi> than the Temple of its <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tenſils:</hi> And Greater <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege</hi> (as of <hi>Korah, &amp;c</hi>) to have Robb'd <hi>Aaron</hi> of his <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> than of his <hi>Veſtments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Deprivation</hi> Robbs the <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Clergy</hi> of their <hi>SPIRIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AL Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> and <hi>Authority:</hi> And therefore is a Greater <hi>Sacrilege</hi> than the Robbing of <hi>Churches,</hi> or <hi>Altars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And is it not worth our ſerious Reflection. That this is the <hi>Act</hi> which <hi>Deprives Ireland</hi> of All their <hi>Civi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Rights, as a <hi>People,</hi> paſt all Help of thoſe <hi>Excuſes,</hi> by which they avoid the <hi>Precedents</hi> of other <hi>Engliſh</hi> Acts, that ſeem to Bear hard upon them? And, by this,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32562:5"/>if <hi>Ireland</hi> will ſtick to that <hi>Sacrilege,</hi> which has been <hi>Impoſed</hi> upon them by the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> they muſt Accept of <hi>Slavery</hi> into the Bargain. But if they had rather be <hi>Slaves</hi> to their <hi>Neighbours,</hi> than <hi>Servants</hi> to <hi>God;</hi> If they will <hi>Chuſe</hi> to Forfeit all <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Title</hi> to their <hi>Eſtates, Lives,</hi> and <hi>Liberty</hi> (not to ſpeak of their <hi>Religion</hi>) and to hold them <hi>Precariouſly,</hi> at the <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Pleaſure</hi> of thoſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who have a different <hi>Intereſt</hi> from them, and are already Grown <hi>Jealous</hi> of them, and Declare they muſt find Ways to <hi>Humble</hi> them; and not ſuffer them to enjoy the Common <hi>Benefit;</hi> and (by the Rules of <hi>Liberty</hi>) the <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Mankind,</hi> which is, To make the Beſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> of their <hi>Labours</hi>—If they will <hi>Chuſe</hi> this, Rather than do <hi>Juſtice</hi> (as I may ſo ſay) to <hi>God,</hi> by <hi>Reſtoring</hi> what they have <hi>Robb'd</hi> from Him; or ſo much as <hi>Acknowledging</hi> that they have done <hi>Amiſs</hi> therein; This <hi>Liberty</hi> they have ſtill left to them: And they may Go on, and Try, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>They</hi> or <hi>God</hi> are the <hi>ſtrongeſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If they ſay, That it is no <hi>Sacrilege</hi> for <hi>Lay-Men</hi> to take upon them to <hi>Diveſt</hi> the <hi>Prieſts</hi> of <hi>God</hi> of their <hi>Purely</hi> Spiritual <hi>Authority:</hi> And that too upon <hi>Purely</hi> Secular <hi>Accounts.</hi> I Refer them to what has been already wrote upon that Subject: And which has yet Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd no Anſwer.</p>
            <p>But take it as they will, if they ſtill remain <hi>Inſenſible</hi> as to the Point of <hi>Conſcience:</hi> Yet if they will not <hi>Rivet</hi> their <hi>Slavery,</hi> by their own <hi>Conſent,</hi> they muſt <hi>Diſown</hi> that <hi>Engliſh Act</hi> Appointing the <hi>New Oaths;</hi> which (as ſaid before) they cannot do, without Reſtoring thoſe who ſuffer Forfeitures by it.</p>
            <p>If they will not do this; Then let them Remember, at leaſt, Others will, That their <hi>Sla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very</hi> Commences with their <hi>Sacrilege.</hi> And it will not be thought <hi>Superſtition</hi> hereafter to obſerve, That the <hi>Providence</hi> of <hi>God</hi> has ſo order'd it, as that this very <hi>Act</hi> which In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volves them in <hi>Sacrilege,</hi> Proves the <hi>Only Act</hi> which <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanſwerably</hi> Deſtroys their <hi>Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>Civil</hi> Rights.</p>
            <p>If we Believe not that there is a <hi>Providence,</hi> we cannot be <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> no, nor good <hi>Deiſts:</hi> And if there be an <hi>All-ſeeing</hi> Providence, Nothing can Eſcape its <hi>Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> or Get out of its <hi>Reach.</hi> In ſhort, if there be ſuch a thing as <hi>Providence</hi> in <hi>God,</hi> there can be no ſuch thing as <hi>Chance;</hi> for the one does neceſſarily Deſtroy the other: We only call that <hi>Chance</hi> where we know not the <hi>Cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since therefore we are Oblig'd to Confeſs, That there is a <hi>Providence,</hi> without which a <hi>Sparrow</hi> does not fall to the Ground; ſurely it may be Permitted, nay, it muſt become our <hi>Duty</hi> ſeriouſly to contemplate ſo very <hi>Legible</hi> a <hi>Character</hi> of <hi>Divine Providence,</hi> in the Falling down of a whole <hi>Nation</hi> from <hi>Freedom</hi> to <hi>Slavery:</hi> And that in ſuch a Remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kable Manner as in the Preſent Caſe; That their <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Freedom</hi> went out, and <hi>Slavery</hi> came in at the ſame Door, which they <hi>Open'd</hi> to let in <hi>Sacrilege;</hi> at leaſt, which they Durſt not <hi>Shut</hi> againſt it. They are not barely <hi>Paſſive</hi> herein, as in relation to the <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Navigation,</hi> &amp;c. before mention'd, wherein <hi>England</hi> bears Hard upon them: But <hi>their own Hands and Tongues have made them to Fall; inſomuch that whoſo ſeeth them, ſhall Laugh them to ſcorn: And all Men that ſee it, ſhall ſay, This hath God done; for they ſhall Perceive that it is his Work.</hi> Theſe <hi>Words</hi> are in one of the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> for the Day of the <hi>Month</hi> on which the <hi>Deprivation</hi> of the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Proteſtant <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy</hi> then in <hi>England</hi> did Commence, by that <hi>Engliſh</hi> Act we have been ſpeaking of, which was the 12th Day of <hi>Feb.</hi> 1691/2 Which as oft as it has Occurr'd, afforded me Matter of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation,</hi> and <hi>Adoring</hi> the <hi>Divine Providence,</hi> in ſo Remarkable an <hi>Inſtance</hi> of it, as was ſhewn <hi>That</hi> Day: And I have Adventur'd to let others Partake of my Thoughts herein. What Uſe they will make of it, is in the Hands of <hi>God</hi> to Diſpoſe. But if this Prompt them not to Conſider their Caſe, in Relation both to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> it will ſtand as a <hi>Witneſs</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, of their having Robb'd <hi>God:</hi> And in the ſame Act Betray'd the <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of their <hi>Country,</hi> who Intruſted them as their <hi>Repreſentatives:</hi> And <hi>Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd</hi> up <hi>Themſelves,</hi> and their <hi>Poſterities,</hi> as Abſolute <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aves,</hi> by the <hi>Methods</hi> they have taken to Aſſert their <hi>Freedom;</hi> contrary to their own <hi>Laws,</hi> as well as the <hi>Laws</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> But <hi>God</hi> will be <hi>Magnify'd,</hi> if we will not ſuffer it in His <hi>Mercies</hi> and <hi>Protection</hi> upon our <hi>Obedience,</hi> yet by His <hi>Judgments</hi> for our <hi>Rebellion</hi> againſt Him.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Dec.</hi> 26. 1698.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Liberavi Animam Meam.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>
               <hi>ERRATA:</hi> Pag 1. l. 12. and p. 2. l. 2. f. <hi>avail</hi> r. <hi>avoid,</hi> l. 29. r. <hi>it was.</hi> p. 4. l 6. f. <hi>their</hi> r. <hi>this.</hi> l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>1. f. <hi>keep.</hi> r. <hi>reap.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:32562:5"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
